<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The original of war, or, The causes of rebellion a sermon preached in the castle of Exon on the 15th of January, 1683, before the Right Reverend Father in God, Thomas Lord Bishop of Exon, and other His Majesties justices of the peace for the county of Devon / by Tho. Long ...</title>
            <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2978</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3712</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12965084</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12965084</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96116</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49126)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 388:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The original of war, or, The causes of rebellion a sermon preached in the castle of Exon on the 15th of January, 1683, before the Right Reverend Father in God, Thomas Lord Bishop of Exon, and other His Majesties justices of the peace for the county of Devon / by Tho. Long ...</title>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 34, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. and F. Collins for Daniel Brown ... and are to be sold by Walter Davies ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96116:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96116:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ORIGINAL of WAR: OR, THE <hi>Cauſes of Rebellion.</hi> A SERMON Preached in the Caſtle of <hi>Exon,</hi> On the 15th of <hi>January,</hi> 1683. BEFORE The Right Reverend Father in God <hi>THOMAS</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exon,</hi> And other His Majeſties JUSTICES of the Peace For the County of <hi>DEVON.</hi> By <hi>THO. LONG,</hi> Prebendary of St. <hi>Peters, Exon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Rebuke the company of ſpearmen, the multitude of the bulls, with the calves of the people, till every one ſubmit himſelf with pieces of ſilver. Scatter thou the people that delight in war,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 68.30.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>—Quem diſcordiae, quem caedes Civium, quem bellum Civile delectat, eum ex finibus humanae naturae exterminandum puto.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicero,</hi> Philip. <hi>13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> and <hi>F. Collins,</hi> for <hi>Daniel Brown</hi> at the <hi>black Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple-bar;</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Walter Davies</hi> in <hi>Amen-corner.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_Bishop">
            <pb facs="tcp:96116:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96116:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Reverend Father in God <hi>THOMAS</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exon,</hi> And other His Majeſties JUSTICES of the Peace For the County of <hi>DEVON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD &amp; GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I <hi>Have the more readily complied with your</hi> Deſires <hi>for</hi> Printing this Sermon, <hi>that I may acquaint the Nation with an</hi> Exemplary inſtance <hi>of</hi> Religion <hi>and</hi> Loyalty; <hi>which I beg your pardon for</hi> Reprinting <hi>in your</hi> Own words, <hi>as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Devon. ſſ.</hi> Ad General. Quarterial. Seſſion. Pacis Dom. Regis tent. apud Caſtr. <hi>Exon.</hi> in &amp; pro Comitat. praed. Secundo die <hi>Octobris,</hi> Anno Regni Dom. noſtri <hi>Caroli</hi> Secundi Dei gratia Angliae, Scotiae, Franciae, &amp; Hiberniae Regis, Fidei Defenſor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Triceſſimo quinto, Anno<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Dom. <hi>1683.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E have been ſo abundantly convinced of the Seditious and Rebellious Practices of the Sectaries and Phanaticks, who through the Courſe of above One hundred years ſince we were firſt infeſted with 'em, have ſcarce afforded this unhappy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom any interval of reſt from their Horrid Treaſons, as that we muſt eſteem 'em, not onely the open Enemies of our Eſtabliſhed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but to all the common Principles of Society and Humanity it ſelf. Wherefore, that we may prevent their Horrid Conſpiracies for the time to come, and ſecure (as much as in us lies) our moſt Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:96116:3"/>KING and the GOVERNMENT from the Fury-and Malice of 'em, we reſolve to put the Severeſt of the Laws (which we find too Eaſie and Gentle, unleſs enlivened by a vigorous Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution) in force againſt 'em.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We Agree and Reſolve, in every Diviſion of this County, to require ſufficient Sureties for the good Abearing and peaceable Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of all ſuch as we may juſtly ſuſpect, or that we can receive any credible Information againſt, that they have been at any Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and Unlawful Meetings, or at any Factious or Seditious Clubs; or that have by any Diſcourſes diſcovered themſelves to be diſaffect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the preſent Eſtabliſhed Government, either in Church or State; or that have been the Authors or Publiſhers of any Seditious Libels; or that ſhall not in all things duely conform themſelves to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Eſtabliſhed Government.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe we have a ſort of Falſe Men, and more perfidious than profeſſed Phanaticks, who either wanting Courage to appear in their own ſhape, or the better to bring about their Treaſonable Deſigns, privately aſſociate with, and encourage the Seditious Clubs of the Sectaries, and with them Plot heartily againſt the Government; and yet, that they may paſs unſuſpected, ſometime appear in the Church with a falſe ſhew of Conformity, onely to ſave their Money, and the better to ſerve their Faction: that we may (if poſſible) diſtinguiſh and know all ſuch dangerous Enemies, we will ſtrictly require all Church-wardens and Conſtables, at all our Monthly Meetings, to give us a full account of all ſuch as do not every Sunday reſort to their own Pariſh-Churches, and are not at the beginning of Divine Service, and do not behave themſelves Orderly and Soberly there, obſerving all ſuch decent Ceremonies as the Laws enjoyn: And that they likewiſe Preſent unto us the Names of all ſuch as have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper in their own Pariſh-Churches Thrice in the Year.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Being fully ſatisfied, as well by the clear Evidence of the late Horrid PLOT, as by our own long and ſad Experience, That the Nonconformiſt Preachers are the Authors and Fomenters of this Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent Faction, and the implacable Enemies of the Eſtabliſhed Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and to whom the late Execrable Treaſons, which have had ſuch diſmal effects in this Kingdom, are principally to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and who by their preſent obſtinate refuſing to Take and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe an Oath and Declaration, <hi>That they do not hold it lawful to take up ARMS againſt the KING, and that they will not endeavour any Alteration of Government either in Church or State;</hi> do neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force
<pb facs="tcp:96116:3"/>us to conclude, that they are ſtill ready to engage themſelves (if not actually engaged) in ſome Rebellious Conſpiracy againſt the KING, and to Invade and Subvert his GOVERNMENT: Wherefore we reſolve in every Pariſh of this County, to leave ſtrict Warrants in the hands of all Conſtables, for the ſeizing of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. And as an encouragement to all Officers and others, that ſhall be inſtrumental in the apprehending of any of them, ſo as they may be brought to Juſtice, we will give and allow Forty ſhillings, as a Reward, for every Nonconformiſt-Preacher that ſhall be ſo ſecured. And we Reſolve to proſecute them and all other ſuch Dangerous E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Government, and common Abſenters from Church, and frequenters of CONVENTICLES, according to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of a Law made in the Five and Thirtieth Year of the Reign of Queen <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> Entituled, <hi>An Act for the keeping Her Majeſties Subjects in due OBEDIENCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly.</hi> That we may never forget the infinite Mercies of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, in the late Wonderful Deliverance of our Gracious KING, and His Deareſt BROTHER, and all His Loyal Subjects, (who were deſigned for a Maſſacre) from the Horrid Conſpiracy of the Phanaticks and their Accomplices; and that we may perpetuate as well our own Thankfulneſs, as their Infamy, that the Generations to come may know their Treachery, and avoid and never truſt men of ſuch Principles more; and alſo, that we our ſelves may perform our publick Duty to Almighty God, before we enter upon the publick Service of our Country: We Order, Reſolve, and Agree, with the Advice and Concurrence of the Right Reverend Father in God, our much Honoured and Worthy Lord BISHOP, to give and beſtow for the Beautifying of the Chappel in the Caſtle of <hi>EXON,</hi> and for the erecting of decent Seats there, Ten pounds: And we will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe give &amp; continue Six pounds to be paid yearly to any one of the Church of <hi>Exon,</hi> whom the ſaid Lord BISHOP ſhall appoint, to read the DIVINE SERVICE, with the Prayers lately appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the day of Thankſgiving on the Ninth of <hi>September</hi> laſt, and to Preach a Sermon exhorting to OBEDIENCE, in the ſaid Chappel, on the firſt day of every General Quarter-Seſſions of the Peace held in the ſaid Caſtle, to begin preciſely at Eight of the Clock in the Morning.</p>
            <p>And may the Mercies of Heaven (which are infinite) always pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect our Religious and Gracious KING, his Deareſt BROTHER, and every Branc of that ROYAL FAMILY; and may all the
<pb facs="tcp:96116:4"/>Treaſonable Conſpiracies of thoſe Rebellious Schiſchmaticks be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways thus happily prevented.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Episcopal_order_to_print">
            <p>That the continued Care of His Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for the County of <hi>DEVON,</hi> for the Safety of His Majeſties Sacred Perſon, the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Publick Peace, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of true Religion, may be fuller known, and have a better Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; I do hereby Order and Require all the CLERGY of my Dioceſs within the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately to publiſh this Order, the next Sunday after it ſhall be tendred to them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. EXON.</signed>
               <signed>Hugo Vaughan, Cler. Pacis Com praed.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_Bishop">
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD &amp; GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>YOu have taken the</hi> right meaſure <hi>for ſecuring our</hi> Peace, <hi>and</hi> rendring unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, <hi>by</hi> rendring unto God the things that are Gods <hi>in the first place. We all owe it to your Piety, R. R. Father, who have</hi> loved our Nation, and built us another Synagogue: <hi>which with all thankfulneſs we</hi> acknowledge; <hi>and may it ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remain</hi> a Houſe of Prayer <hi>for</hi> thoſe ends <hi>to which you have</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned <hi>and</hi> reconſecrated <hi>it, by your</hi> preſence <hi>and</hi> Devotion. <hi>When I ſaw the</hi> Heads of our County <hi>following the</hi> Guide of their Souls, <hi>and like</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron <hi>on the Mount</hi> ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out their hands <hi>with their</hi> hearts <hi>unto God</hi> in Prayer, <hi>it ſeemed to me a</hi> good Omen <hi>of</hi> Succeſs <hi>and</hi> Victory <hi>against thoſe</hi> Amalekites <hi>that are ſtill conſpiring against us</hi> in the Vallies. <hi>For ſuch as</hi> you, <hi>who make it your buſineſs to</hi> ſerve God and the King, <hi>are</hi> the Chariots of Iſrael, and the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thereof: <hi>In</hi> you <hi>we may ſee</hi> Righteouſneſs and Peace <hi>embracing</hi> and kiſſing each other; <hi>and may they never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, that attempt to put</hi> them <hi>or</hi> you <hi>aſunder.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96116:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And now I beſeech you, R. R. Father, and worthy Gentlemen,</hi> ſuffer a word of Exhortation; <hi>which is, that you would bend your</hi> united Force <hi>againſt that</hi> Profaneneſs <hi>and</hi> Debauchery, <hi>which, as it is an</hi> effect <hi>of our</hi> former Diviſions <hi>and</hi> War, <hi>ſo it will be the</hi> cauſe <hi>of</hi> new Confuſions, <hi>and drawing down the Wrath of God on the Land. For if ſuch</hi> men of Belial <hi>as are ſtill</hi> fighting againſt God, <hi>blaſpheming his</hi> Holy Name <hi>by</hi> accurſed Oaths <hi>and</hi> damnable Imprecations; <hi>that own no other</hi> Deity <hi>but the</hi> Luſts <hi>of their</hi> upper &amp; nether bellies, <hi>and ſacrifice more of their</hi> time <hi>and</hi> Eſtates <hi>to</hi> Bacchus <hi>and</hi> Venus, <hi>than to their</hi> God and Saviour, <hi>and,</hi> Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than-<hi>like,</hi> ſport themſelves <hi>n the</hi> waters of the Sanctuary, <hi>ſcoffing at all things that are</hi> Sacred, <hi>and think themſelves</hi> ſo great, <hi>that no man</hi> durſt put a hook in their noſtrils, <hi>or</hi> reprove <hi>them, though never ſo</hi> friendly, <hi>and in the</hi> Name of God, <hi>be permitted to</hi> riot it in the day-time, <hi>we may expect an</hi> approaching night <hi>of as much</hi> blackneſs and darkneſs, <hi>as</hi> violent ſtorms <hi>and</hi> tempeſts, <hi>as</hi> hitherto <hi>(God be thanked) hath paſt over our heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And becauſe</hi> Tipling <hi>and</hi> Brothel-houſes <hi>and the</hi> Nurſeries <hi>of theſe</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous vices, <hi>where men ſacrifice more of their</hi> time <hi>and</hi> Eſtates <hi>to their</hi> ungodly Luſts, <hi>than to their</hi> God and Saviour; <hi>let thoſe</hi> Neſts <hi>and</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles <hi>of</hi> unclean Locuſts <hi>and</hi> devouring Caterpillars, <hi>which do even</hi> cover the Land, <hi>and though they have the</hi> faces of men, <hi>yet under them they carry the</hi> hearts of beaſts, <hi>and the</hi> ſtings of fiery Serpents, <hi>be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. I know there may be ſome</hi> Silver-ſmiths <hi>that will plead for</hi> theſe Shrines of the great Goddeſs Diana, which bring no ſmall gain to the Crafts-men: <hi>But certainly if the</hi> time <hi>and</hi> Treaſure <hi>which is ſpent and</hi> ſpilt <hi>by theſe</hi> Debaucheries <hi>in</hi> Idleneſs, <hi>and upon their</hi> Luſts, <hi>were employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their</hi> dayly Labours <hi>and</hi> honeſt Callings <hi>the King would have a</hi> far greater, <hi>as well as a</hi> better Revenue <hi>and</hi> Aid, <hi>than from all thoſe</hi> Augean Stables. <hi>Theſe are thoſe</hi> Devils Chappels, <hi>which in many places he ſet up for</hi> himſelf, <hi>at the</hi> very entrance into God's Houſe; <hi>where his</hi> Chaplains <hi>dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attend</hi> his Service, <hi>but eſpecially on thoſe</hi> Holy-days <hi>which are ſet apart for</hi> God's Worſhip; <hi>and from</hi> hence <hi>there are as many</hi> Oaths <hi>and</hi> Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations <hi>for</hi> Vengeance <hi>and</hi> Damnation <hi>ſent up againſt Heaven, as there are</hi> Prayers <hi>and</hi> Supplications <hi>for</hi> Pardon <hi>and</hi> Salvation <hi>in the</hi> Churches of God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96116:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And how</hi> great Provocations <hi>theſe are to our</hi> Holy God, <hi>your own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the great and</hi> dayly trouble <hi>occaſioned by ſuch</hi> Riots, <hi>may inform you: for from hence proceed</hi> Thefts, Whoredoms, Baſtardies, <hi>Brauls and</hi> Quarrels, <hi>which are proſecuted by</hi> expenſive <hi>and</hi> ruining Law-ſuits, mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Limbs, <hi>and</hi> ſhedding of innocent Bloud. <hi>Theſe are the</hi> Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>of</hi> Vagabonds <hi>and</hi> Robbers, <hi>the</hi> Hoſpitals <hi>of</hi> incurable Fools <hi>and</hi> Madmen; <hi>where men are</hi> beſotted, <hi>bereaved of</hi> reaſon <hi>and</hi> ſtrength, <hi>and made uncapable of any</hi> good Employment: <hi>The very</hi> Peſthouſes <hi>of the Nation, where</hi> Diſeaſes <hi>are propagated, and</hi> Infirmities <hi>intailed on</hi> ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Generations. <hi>By theſe</hi> Circean Cups, men <hi>are transformed into</hi> beaſts; <hi>and by their</hi> looks <hi>and their</hi> language <hi>you may know them: for</hi> Vix hominem ſonant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe were the</hi> Apollyons <hi>that</hi> deſtroyed <hi>the late Kings</hi> Armies, <hi>his</hi> Forts <hi>and</hi> Garriſons, <hi>and reduced him to</hi> more ſtraights <hi>than the Armies of his</hi> Adverſaries; <hi>who when they ſhould be</hi> fighting againſt the Kings E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, <hi>were</hi> fighting againſt God; <hi>and</hi> diſcharging Vollies of Oaths againſt Heaven, <hi>when they ſhould have been</hi> praying <hi>for</hi> mercy <hi>and</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs <hi>from thence. Theſe</hi> hardned the hearts <hi>of the</hi> Kings Enemies, <hi>and</hi> alienated the affections <hi>of his</hi> Subjects <hi>as if the</hi> Cauſe <hi>could not be</hi> good, <hi>that was defended by</hi> ſuch Inſtruments: <hi>for they brought an</hi> evil Report <hi>on a</hi> righteous Cauſe, <hi>as if their</hi> Prince <hi>were like</hi> that Party, <hi>or</hi> Gallio-<hi>like,</hi> cared for none of thoſe things. <hi>It was doubtleſs by and for the</hi> wickedneſs <hi>of</hi> theſe men, <hi>that</hi> ſo good a Prince, <hi>and</hi> ſo juſt a Cauſe <hi>was overthrown: and</hi> if we ſtill do wickedly, (<hi>though as yet we have no</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Enemies) <hi>the Mouth of the Lord, which is able to do it, hath ſaid,</hi> Ye ſhall be deſtroyed, both you and your King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore I beſeech you who have</hi> Power <hi>and</hi> Authority <hi>from</hi> God <hi>and the</hi> King, <hi>vigorouſly and unanimouſly to endeavour the</hi> Suppreſſion <hi>of thoſe</hi> Seminaries <hi>of</hi> ſin <hi>and</hi> uncleanneſs, <hi>which</hi> provoke God, <hi>and bring the</hi> Government <hi>into</hi> Contempt; <hi>and then we may hope that God will ſtill</hi> ſuppreſs our Enemies, <hi>and eſtabliſh us on the</hi> ſure Foundations <hi>of</hi> Peace <hi>and</hi> Righteouſneſs: <hi>which is and ſhall be the hearty Prayer of,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Exon,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 21. 1683.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My Lord and Gentlemen,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble and hearty Servant, for God, his Church, and the King, <hi>THO. LONG.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96116:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>St. <hi>JAMES 4.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>From whence come wars and fightings among you? come they not hence, even from your luſts which war in your members?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing to ſpeak to ſo ſolemn an Audience, I could not think of a more ſeaſonable and proper Subject, than to commend unto you, eſpecially R. R. Father in God, and worthy Gentlemen who are in Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the <hi>PEACE,</hi> and <hi>Enquiry</hi> into the Cauſes of <hi>WAR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Text ſeems to be a <hi>Writ of Enquiry:—From whence come wars?</hi> In the due execution whereof, you may do God and the King, your ſelves and your Country, moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Service. For in this Text you have a diſcovery of the firſt moſt ſecret motions that tend to <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> which, as it is ſaid of the <hi>Baſilisk,</hi> being firſt ſeen, they die; but if they ſurprize us, we periſh.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore wave all formalities and delays, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your humble <hi>Sollicitor</hi> to take immediate cognizance of the <hi>merits of the Cauſe;</hi> that OLD CAUSE which hath formerly involved the three Nations in War and Confuſion, and is like to ſet us all on a flame a ſecond time. And I doubt not to produce ſuch <hi>clear and unqueſtionable evidence</hi> concerning the <hi>matter of fact,</hi> that not one (though inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed and prejudiced perſon) ſhall return an <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> but agree fully in the <hi>Verdict</hi> with St. <hi>James,</hi> That <hi>the wars and fightings among our ſelves</hi> can proceed from no other cauſe, but <hi>thoſe luſts that war in our members.</hi> And in this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96116:6"/>I dare make every man a <hi>Juror,</hi> being as well under the Oath of <hi>God</hi> in his <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> as the Oath of the <hi>King</hi> in his <hi>Allegiance:</hi> both which oblige him to <hi>diſcover and bring to condign puniſhment</hi> thoſe luſts that fight againſt <hi>God,</hi> againſt the Peace of <hi>our Soveraign Lord the King,</hi> and the temporal and eternal Peace of <hi>our own Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three things the Text directs us to enquire into.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The matter of Fact: <hi>Wars and fightings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Perſons engaged: <hi>Among you, or between your ſelves, (viz.)</hi> the twelve Tribes to whom St. <hi>James</hi> writes this Epiſtle.</item>
               <item>3. The Original whence theſe Wars came; which our Apoſtle aſſures us, was from no other cauſe, but <hi>thoſe luſts which did war in their members.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> of the matter of Fact; which was more than <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Stirs and Heats,</hi> (as ſome term them) there was ſome fire and flames; and <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith our Apoſtle, <hi>how great a matter a little fire kindleth!</hi> it proceeded to Open Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Murther. For although by Gods juſt Judgment upon them, they had been for above an hundred years un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power and Government of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and owned no King but <hi>Caeſar,</hi> by whom they were permitted the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of their Religion, Laws, and Liberties, under the eaſie tribute of one peny yearly for each perſon, which was the ordinary pay of a Labourer or Souldier for one days ſervice: yet did they not onely often rebel againſt their <hi>lawful Governours</hi> on the account of that Tribute, but fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently by more than Civil Wars did execute moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and bloudy Fights among themſelves, being divided into many reſtleſs Factions, each ſtriving to be uppermoſt, until they were all ruined.</p>
            <p>This our Apoſtle plainly expreſſeth, <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>Ye fight and war;</hi> and again, <hi>ye kill, and deſire to have;</hi> (i. e.) to get
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96116:6"/>dominion and unlawful poſſeſſions: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the word is, and it ſeems to refer to a Generation of men that called them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Zealots,</hi> who under a pretence of Juſtice and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, made it lawful to kill and deſtroy all that oppoſed their ingroſſing the Power, Wealth, and Trade of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for that was the Religion of thoſe men. And thus began thoſe unnatural Wars: the People were perſwaded by theſe <hi>Zealots,</hi> that their Religion, Laws, and Liberties were invaded by their <hi>King,</hi> that <hi>Prince of Peace, the anointed and Holy One of God.</hi> Againſt whom the great Council and ſome chief Prieſts ſtirred up the People, and conſpired to put him to death: And having all the Factions at their beck againſt him, as their <hi>common Enemy,</hi> that would let in the <hi>Romans</hi> upon them; and having by many <hi>intolerable affronts and indignities driven him from his Royal City,</hi> and <hi>hunted him from place to place,</hi> they corrupted a <hi>Judas</hi> to betray him for a <hi>ſum of money;</hi> and by <hi>Subornation of falſe Witneſſes,</hi> and a <hi>Pagan Judge,</hi> and <hi>mockery of Juſtice,</hi> they murthered him as it were at the Gates of his great City <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> whoſe thirſt of bloud he had a little before en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to quench by a floud of tears: <hi>O Jeruſalem, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, which killeſt the Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. This our Apoſtle obſerves, <hi>ch.</hi> 5. 6. <hi>Ye have condemned and killed,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>Juſt One;</hi> Parallel to <hi>Acts</hi> 3.14. <hi>Ye denied the Holy One and the Juſt, and deſired a Murtherer to be granted unto you.</hi> And now that the Royal ſence was digged down, what could be expected but a deluge of Bloud, even the days of Vengeance, <hi>wherein all things that were written were to be fulfilled?</hi> Luke 21.22.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Judgment was to begin firſt at the houſe of God.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly we find, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.9. that <hi>Some of the Synagogue of the Libertines and Cyrenians,</hi> &amp;c. accuſed St. <hi>Stephen</hi> the Proto-Martyr. For <hi>they being not able to reſiſt the wiſdom and the ſpirit by which he ſpake;</hi> and by his ſharp but juſt reproofs, <hi>ch.</hi> 7. 5. being <hi>cut to the heart, v.</hi> 54. the People
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96116:7"/>Elders and Scribes caught him, and brought him to the Council; and <hi>ſet up falſe witneſſes,</hi> which ſaid, <hi>that he had ſpoke blaſphemous words againſt Moſes and againſt God,</hi> and would <hi>change their cuſtoms,</hi> ch. 6. 11. And him they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted with a rage that reached up to Heaven: for they <hi>gnaſhed on him with their teeth,</hi> and <hi>cried with a loud voice</hi> for his bloud; and <hi>ſtopped their ears</hi> to all ſober counſels; and <hi>ran upon him with one accord, and ſtoned him, calling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, and praying for his enemies: Lord, lay not this ſin to their charge,</hi> Acts 7.60.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Herod</hi> their <hi>uſurping king vexed the whole church; impriſoned St. Peter, and ſlew James the Brother of our Lord with the ſword.</hi> And thoſe men <hi>of whom the world was not worthy,</hi> were counted worthy to die; and die they did like worthy men: for <hi>they took joyfully the ſpoiling of their goods,</hi> and <hi>had trial of cruel mockings and ſcourgings, bonds and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment;</hi> and being tempted to <hi>deny the faith,</hi> choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be <hi>ſawn aſunder and ſlain with the ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What havock was made of the Flock of Chriſt by theſe <hi>grievous Wolves,</hi> after that the <hi>chief Shepherds</hi> were <hi>ſmitten,</hi> is too large to be repeated: Onely as <hi>Geographers</hi> are wont to deſcribe great Countries and Cities, Battels and Devaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in a little <hi>Map;</hi> I ſhall preſent you with a <hi>proſpect</hi> of thoſe Wars as it was delineated by our Saviours own hand; whereof it was impoſſible but every tittle ſhould be true. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.9. He ſays, <hi>They ſhould deliver one another to the council, and beat them in their ſynagogues:</hi> That <hi>brother ſhould betray brother to death, and the father the ſon; and children ſhould riſe up againſt their parents, and cauſe them to be put to death: that a mans foes ſhould be thoſe of his own houſe; and whoever did kill his diſciples, ſhould think that he did God good ſervice: That there ſhould follow thoſe wars great afflictions peſtilences &amp; famines, ſuch as had not been from the beginning of the world: That they ſhould fall by the edge of the ſword, and be led captive into all Nations; and Jeruſalem
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96116:7"/>ſhould be trodden down of the Gentiles.</hi> Luke 21.23. for their enemies ſhould <hi>caſt a trench about them, and keep them in on every ſide, and lay them even with the ground, and her children within her, until there were not one ſtone left upon another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſhortly after our Saviours death, began theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; of which we have ſome account in the <hi>Acts,</hi> ch. 5. 36. <hi>Theudas boaſting himſelf to be an extraordinary perſon</hi> (as it was foretold that <hi>falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhould ariſe and deceive many</hi>) <hi>began a Rebellion with</hi> 400 men, whom he diſſuaded to pay Tribute to <hi>Caeſar; who was ſlain, and all that obeyed him were brought to nought.</hi> Then <hi>Judas of Galilee</hi> on the ſame occaſion <hi>drew much people after him and he and his party periſhed,</hi> Acts 5.36, 37. Then <hi>Bar-Jeſus</hi> a falſe Prophet ſought to <hi>diſcredit our Saviours Miracles</hi> by his <hi>Sorcery,</hi> Acts 13.6. Another falſe Prophet <hi>led out</hi> 4000 <hi>men into the wilderneſs who were Murderers,</hi> Acts 21.38. theſe, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſays, increaſed to 30000, but were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by <hi>Felix.</hi> 8400 were ſlain at <hi>Joppa,</hi> 20000 at <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> not one eſcaping; 50000 at <hi>Delta,</hi> and a great ſlaughter was made of them that followed <hi>Simon</hi> a Galile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, by <hi>Coponius.</hi> See <hi>Joſephus l.</hi> 2. 19. 22. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother great Maſſacre on <hi>Eleazar</hi> and his Party, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to <hi>ſacrifice and pray</hi> for the welfare of <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that theſe turbulent <hi>Jews</hi> finding no ſucceſs in their attempts againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> turned their Swords againſt each other; and they who boaſted moſt of being <hi>true Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> were <hi>true Iſhmaelites,</hi> that <hi>had their hands lifted up againſt every man, and every mans hand againſt them.</hi> The tribe of <hi>Ephraim againſt Manaſſe, and both againſt Judah;</hi> City againſt City, and Brother againſt Brother: they who called themſelves the <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Zealous,</hi> threw off their Cloaks, and appeared to be <hi>Sicarii,</hi> very <hi>Thieves and Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throats,</hi> as <hi>Joſephus</hi> calls them. <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that had been a <hi>City at unity within her ſelf,</hi> was by theſe men crumbled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96116:8"/>to Factions, and made an <hi>Aceldema,</hi> or <hi>field of blood,</hi> which was <hi>ſhed as water on every ſide of Jeruſalem.</hi> Mount <hi>Sion, the glory of the whole earth,</hi> was like Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> ſurroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with <hi>blackneſs and tempeſts, and the ſounds of trumpets.</hi> The <hi>holy lamps</hi> were extinguiſhed, and NEW LIGHTS ſet up on every Turret, which burnt them to the ground. The <hi>Temple</hi> had no other <hi>Sacrifices</hi> but heaps of <hi>ſlain men,</hi> and the <hi>blood of the Prieſt ſhed before the Altar,</hi> whom the <hi>Zealots</hi> ſlew with as little regret, as the <hi>Prieſts</hi> were wont to ſlay the beaſts for Sacrifice. All ſacred things were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned, and prophane things accounted ſacred. Having nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>King</hi> nor <hi>Prieſt</hi> left, <hi>every one did what ſeemed good in his own eyes;</hi> and like <hi>Cain</hi> that had <hi>ſlain his Brother,</hi> thought <hi>every one he met would ſlay him;</hi> and therefore dealt with him as an enemy. Here you might ſee three <hi>Independent Armies</hi> ſtrugling in the bowels of their common mother <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and putting her into ſo many throws and pangs, as cauſed her diſſolution: <hi>John</hi> the Prieſt againſt <hi>Eleazar</hi> the Religious, and both againſt <hi>Simon</hi> the Zealot; who being defeated, ſlew his Wife and Children firſt, and then himſelf. Here the Souldiers eat their leathern girdles for hunger, and women their Children of a ſpan-long; the aged and young dying for Famine; the rich and the Nobles ſlain with the Sword, and none to make lamentation over them, or to bury the dead. This was the condition of that <hi>Holy land,</hi> when the <hi>Kingdom of Iſrael</hi> degenerated into a <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any mans heart be not affected with this ſhort relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Jewiſh Wars, let him read thoſe larger Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries which their Countryman <hi>Joſephus,</hi> who was an eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſs of thoſe confuſions, tranſcribed from the Originals written with their Swords in Blood. And he muſt have a heart harder than thoſe <hi>Swords,</hi> or the <hi>Adamant</hi> it ſelf, that is not mollified by ſo much humane blood, but ſtill retains an edge and appetite for War; which none can reliſh,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96116:8"/>but they who have ſurfeited on too much Plenty, and too long Peace; and being diſpleaſed with themſelves, by their inſatiable <hi>luſts,</hi> and diſtracted <hi>Conſciences,</hi> ſeek to find eaſe and diverſions, as the Devils do, by drawing others into the ſame condemnation; like thoſe <hi>unhappy Princes,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſturbed by frequent <hi>Seditions</hi> of their Subjects at home, do <hi>invade</hi> the Dominions of their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> and make their Territories <hi>the Seat of War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>luſts</hi> that did <hi>war in their members,</hi> carryed on the war againſt the <hi>head</hi> and <hi>heart</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> which minds us of</p>
            <p>The ſecond particular to be enquired of: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde bella in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vos?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this was no <hi>neceſſitous people,</hi> no <hi>Highlanders,</hi> or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Deſarts of <hi>Arabia Petrea,</hi> but of <hi>Canaan which flowed with milk and honey</hi> for the pooreſt; they were fed with <hi>the flower of the kidneys of wheat</hi> to ſtrengthen them, and drank <hi>of the generous blood of the grape</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort their hearts, and <hi>Rivers of Oyl to make them of a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful countenance.</hi> God <hi>rained fleſh among them as thick as duſt, and feathered fowl as the ſand of the Sea.</hi> Heaven and earth contributed all their Treaſures, to make them a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py people.</p>
            <p>But the proviſion that God gave them for the comfort of their lives, they uſed as provocations to their luſts; and as <hi>Jeſurun</hi> of old, <hi>they waxed fat and kicked: they forſook God that made them, and lightly eſteemed the rock of their Salvation.</hi> And from hence came thoſe Wars.—<hi>He deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their power into captivity, and their beauty to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hands: he gave his people over to the Sword, and was wroth with his inheritance.</hi> The Surfeit of a long-continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Peace and Plenty, is fatal unto ſenſual men; it puts them into ſuch <hi>Feavouriſh Diſtempers,</hi> and <hi>freaks of madneſs,</hi> that they can neither indure the <hi>diſeaſe</hi> nor the <hi>remedy,</hi> but ſeek to <hi>deſtroy</hi> thoſe that come to <hi>ſave</hi> them.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96116:9"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whence come theſe Wars among you?</hi> Who had as often felt the diſmal conſequences of war, as they had provoked God by their murmurings, their ingratitude for good, and <hi>luſting after evil things.</hi> They could not forget their ſore bondage in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and their miſerable captivity under the inſulting <hi>Babylonians,</hi> who <hi>cryed, Down with them even to the ground,</hi> ROOT and BRANCH, <hi>that the name of Iſrael may no more be had in remembrance:</hi> and they were ſcarce recovered out of thoſe confuſions which <hi>Antiochus Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> had brought upon them, (ſee 1 <hi>Maccab.</hi> 1.11.) who drew them into a <hi>Rebellious Covenant,</hi> and proudly entred into their <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> and took away <hi>the golden Ornaments, and the Crown, and the hidden treaſures;</hi> and made great <hi>Maſſacres,</hi> and <hi>covered all the houſe of Jacob with confuſion:</hi> he <hi>laid waſte their Sanctuaries</hi> as a wilderneſs, and <hi>ſhed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood on every ſide of Jeruſalem:</hi> he <hi>forbad their offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and ſacrifices</hi> in the Temple, <hi>polluted their Sabbaths,</hi> and <hi>Feſtival days;</hi> ſet up <hi>Altars</hi> and <hi>Chappels</hi> of <hi>Idols:</hi> leſt their Children <hi>uncircumciſed,</hi> to the end that they might <hi>forget the Law;</hi> and changed all the <hi>Ordinances.</hi> He mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the Prieſts of the moſt high God, and ruled all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own ungodly luſts; driving the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſecret places, whereſoever they could flee for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour.</p>
            <p>But God had by many miracles of mercy reſtored them out of all theſe Calamities, to a good degree of happineſs; their <hi>Temple</hi> was <hi>rebuilt,</hi> their <hi>Laws preſerved;</hi> the <hi>uniform worſhip</hi> of God at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> eſtabliſhed, <hi>whither the Tribes went up to Worſhip, and to give thanks to the Name of the Lord.</hi> God fixed his <hi>Shekinah,</hi> and <hi>dwelt among them</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; he met them in <hi>the beauty of holineſs,</hi> and made them <hi>joyful in his houſe of prayer.</hi> And <hi>to all this glory he added a defence;</hi> for during all the time of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> as long as they ſought the Lord, he made them to proſper. No Nation had a God ſo great, Laws and Statutes ſo good, a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96116:9"/>Land ſo fruitful, Victories ſo ſignal and frequent; that the dread and terrour of them was fallen upon the Nations round about them; and every man might <hi>ſit under his own Vine,</hi> and under <hi>Gods Vine too,</hi> and ſing <hi>the Song of David: Happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe, yea bleſſed are the people who have the Lord for their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What poſſible imagination could men at ſuch a height of felicity (if the very <hi>height</hi> had not made them <hi>giddy</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of bettering their condition by <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Fightings?</hi> Or what in reaſon could they think of, but to ſecure their preſent enjoyments by <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> to <hi>God, Obedience</hi> to their <hi>Governours,</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> among <hi>themſelves?</hi> But this unhappineſs we have all derived from <hi>Adam,</hi> that <hi>Paradiſe it ſelf</hi> will not content us, unleſs we may <hi>eat of the forbidden fruit:</hi> we <hi>nauſeate Manna it ſelf,</hi> unleſs we may have ſomewhat to <hi>gratifie our Luſts, which war againſt our Souls.</hi> And <hi>hence come wars and fightings among us, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from our luſts, which war in our members.</hi> Which is the laſt branch of our Enquiry, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the Original of all our <hi>Wars,</hi> is <hi>thoſe luſts that war in our members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The method to effect a Cure, as in the natural, ſo in the body politick, is firſt to find out the true cauſe: which in this of <hi>War</hi> is like that of the <hi>Hectick Fever,</hi> which at firſt is <hi>hard to be known,</hi> but <hi>eaſily cured;</hi> but at length is <hi>eaſily diſcerned,</hi> and <hi>difficultly cured.</hi> For as in thoſe <hi>lingring Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> there are little indiſcernable <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> lurking in the <hi>bloud,</hi> and circulating with it, which in time ferment the whole <hi>maſs,</hi> and <hi>ſet the whole courſe of Nature on fire:</hi> So <hi>thoſe luſts which war in our members,</hi> and the faculties of our Souls, have a ſecret, and to our ſelves at leaſt, if not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, an indiſcernable motion, until <hi>Temptations</hi> and <hi>Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities</hi> are preſented; and then the <hi>ſenſual appetite</hi> is in a <hi>Commotion,</hi> and <hi>offers violence</hi> to his <hi>Reaſon, Religion,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience.</hi> And thus, as St. <hi>James</hi> deſcribes it, <hi>ch.</hi> 1. 14. <hi>Every man is tempted when he is drawn aſide of his own luſts,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96116:10"/>and enticed.</hi> There is a <hi>ſecret bent</hi> of our Spirits after evil things, which forceth us; and there are <hi>flattering allurements</hi> in the Objects, which entice us; ſuch as the <hi>luſts of the fleſh, unclean pleaſures;</hi> the <hi>luſts of the eyes,</hi> riches and large poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; and the <hi>pride of life,</hi> power, dominion, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe: and between <hi>our luſts</hi> and <hi>theſe objects</hi> ſin is brought forth. So that <hi>all lust</hi> is ſeated in our <hi>inordinate deſires: I had not known lust,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, except the law had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not covet.</hi> For the <hi>iraſcible faculties</hi> of the Soul are but as ſo many <hi>Ruffians,</hi> (ſuch as Anger and Malice, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and Revenge) to execute the wills of the fleſh: but by theſe the ſinner is put into <hi>a ſtate of war</hi> with himſelf: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there is a <hi>Seditious Party</hi> that <hi>wars in our members; the fleſh luſting against the ſpirit, and the ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the fleſh:</hi> and theſe two <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>are ſet in battel aray against each other,</hi> Gal. 5.17. And <hi>the law of the members,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>warreth against the law of the mind.</hi> So impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and ſubtle are theſe luſts, that they too often ſurprize even good men, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> complains of himſelf, <hi>leading him captive;</hi> hindring him from <hi>doing the good that he would,</hi> and hurrying him on <hi>to do the evil he would not, Rom.</hi> 7.23. Hence it is that the Philoſopher calls theſe luſts <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>beaſtly luſts,</hi> not onely from their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs and ſenſuality, their unreaſonableneſs and ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernableneſs, but their ravenous cruelty, and ferine quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; overturning and renting all that ſtands in their way, breaking all bonds of Reaſon and Religion, Law and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; ſacrificing not onely the welfare of others, but their own health and peace, yea thoſe very members in which they war, to the ſatisfaction of theſe luſts: as <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus,</hi> when his Phyſician told him <hi>he muſt leave his intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, or loſe his eyes,</hi> cryed, <hi>Vale amicum lumen; Farewel, dear eyes;</hi> as if his luſts were more dear. So true is that of the Prophet, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57.20. <hi>The wicked are like the troubled Sea that cannot reſt: there is no peace to the wicked, ſaith my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96116:10"/>
            <p>The man that gives up the reins to his luſts, is no longer <hi>Sui juris,</hi> but under the moſt abſolute Tyrants, whoſe Will is their onely Law; where that bids them go, they go; and what that bids them do, they do, though to their utter undoing. In vain doth <hi>Conſcience</hi> take on it the Office of a <hi>Monitor,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> of a <hi>Speaker,</hi> to give their <hi>Reprimands;</hi> they do but provoke the rage and outcires of the <hi>multitude</hi> of Luſts that can endure no controul. <hi>Reaſon</hi> is dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſilenced; the uſurping <hi>Vice</hi> is got into the Chair, and <hi>eſtabliſheth Iniquity by the Law</hi> of <hi>Sic volo, ſic jubeo;</hi> and all the <hi>five Senſes,</hi> like ſo many <hi>officious members,</hi> are ready to execute the Commands of thoſe unruly Luſts.</p>
            <p>Who can wonder that the man who lives in oppoſition to the expreſs Commands of God, and ſlights his own appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of Gods everlaſting wrath, for every <hi>trifling luſt,</hi> ſhould, when the greater temptations of <hi>Dominion</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> of <hi>killing and taking poſſeſſion</hi> of <hi>Crowns</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> are preſented, be the Contrivers and Proſecutors of <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt their <hi>King?</hi> That man cannot truly love or fear the <hi>King,</hi> who <hi>beareth the Sword that can onely kill the body,</hi> who neither loves nor fears <hi>God,</hi> who <hi>is able to deſtroy body and ſoul in hell.</hi> Hence it is that <hi>Solomon</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.11. <hi>The wicked man ſeeketh onely Rebellion.</hi> For having loſt the peace of his own Conſcience by <hi>fighting againſt God,</hi> and having ſinned away the uſe of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>ſober counſels</hi> by his contumacy, like the evil ſpirit that was caſt out of the man, <hi>he findeth no reſt,</hi> but roves up and down, to aſſociate Legions of others as bad as himſelf, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the peace of others. And <hi>hence come wars and fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings among us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now it is eaſie to turn the Scene, and from the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de inter vos,</hi> to enquire <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde inter nos?</hi> From whence come wars and fightings <hi>among us?</hi> For as to matter of fact, if the Wars of any Nation under Heaven can paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96116:11"/>thoſe of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ours do; and in ſome reſpects (conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we are <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) have outdone them. For have not we as obſtinately reſiſted and fought againſt the God of Heaven, though he have placed us in <hi>a fruitful Land,</hi> and fed us with <hi>Manna?</hi> Have not we ſtill murmured, and tempted him, <hi>requiring meat for our luſts?</hi> Have we not refuſed all thoſe means and overtures of ſalvation which the Son of God hath offered us? and do we not ſtill refuſe to do <hi>the things belonging to our peace?</hi> Yea, with the filthy <hi>Gadarens,</hi> we have even <hi>forced him to depart out of our coaſt,</hi> and preferred our <hi>Swine</hi> before our <hi>Saviour.</hi> We have made our great Lord to <hi>ſerve</hi> under our baſeſt luſts: We have ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicul'd him by <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> and <hi>falſe Chriſts,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, he is in the deſert fields, or in the ſecret chambers,</hi> when he taught openly in the Temple. We have falſly accuſed him as <hi>an enemy to Caeſar,</hi> and Patron of <hi>Rebellion;</hi> and ſo have <hi>crucified afreſh to our ſelves the Son of God, and put him to open ſhame:</hi> which if the <hi>Jews</hi> had known, as we profeſs to know him, they would not have done, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8. for <hi>had they known, they would not have crucified the Lord of Glory.</hi> Theſe were the grand cauſes of the final deſtruction of the <hi>Jewiſh Nation,</hi> and theſe provocations had brought <hi>us</hi> ſo nigh to utter confuſion, that nothing but a Miracle of Mercy could prevent us from falling into it. It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore high time to <hi>ſearch out</hi> thoſe Sacrilegious <hi>Achans,</hi> and diſobedient <hi>Jonahs</hi> that have raiſed ſuch <hi>Storms</hi> and <hi>Wars</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us: and we ſhall find them within our own breaſts, even thoſe <hi>luſts that war in our members:</hi> for our Saviour hath aſſured us, that <hi>from within, out of the heart of man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed evil thoughts</hi> firſt, and then <hi>murders;</hi> yea thoſe very <hi>thougts</hi> are accounted as <hi>murther</hi> by our Saviour; and <hi>if there be bitter envying and ſtrife in our hearts,</hi> our Apoſtle tells us, that notwithſtanding our pretences to Wiſdom and Holineſs, we are <hi>earthly, ſenſual, and deviliſh,</hi> Jam. 3.15.</p>
            <p>To make this Enquiry more plain, I ſhall onely premiſe,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96116:11"/>That in a <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> ſo well eſtabliſhed as ours are, where we have all things <hi>neceſſary to Salvation</hi> in the one, all things neceſſary to <hi>preſerve our Liberty and Property</hi> in the other, all deſirable Peace and Plenty for our Perſons and Families, it muſt be our <hi>luſting after evil things</hi> that cauſeth wicked men to diſquiet themſelves and others: Of which this may ſerve as a Demonſtration, that they who would put us into a ſtate of <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> having no <hi>preſent or real grievances</hi> to amuſe the people withal, do raiſe up their old Goblins of <hi>fears and jealouſies</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Tyranny.</hi> But as it is a folly to trouble our ſelves with what <hi>may be,</hi> when it is more probable that it <hi>may not be;</hi> ſo it is the character of a wicked man, to <hi>fear where no fear is,</hi> and a great degree of madneſs, to fall on our <hi>own Swords,</hi> when we are purſued onely by our <hi>own Shadows.</hi> And the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience which we <hi>our ſelves</hi> have had, as well as the <hi>Jewiſh Nation,</hi> may convince us, that thoſe very perſons that frighted both them and us with a <hi>Venient Romani, The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans will come and take away our place and Nation, and change our Laws and Religion,</hi> were thoſe very men that did what they ſuggeſted the <hi>Romans</hi> would do.</p>
            <p>'Tis our Saviour's advice, that we <hi>take no thoughts for the morrow,</hi> (i. e.) that we be not too ſollicitous about fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture events which are not in our power, but carefully do the duties of the preſent day; and <hi>be content with ſuch things as we have,</hi> and <hi>commit our ſelves to him in well-doing: for God hath ſaid, he will never leave nor forſake</hi> ſuch. But if after Gods redeeming of us out of all our troubles by an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hand,</hi> we ſhall return again to our old follies and ungodly luſts, againſt his expreſs Precepts and Threats, we may in vain expect that God ſhould work <hi>another Miracle</hi> for us, that have made ſo little improvement of the <hi>former.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore proceed with my Evidence, that it is only from our luſts that war in our members, whence wars and fightings come among us.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96116:12"/>
            <p>For firſt, we are not under the power of a <hi>Heathen</hi> or <hi>Forreign Prince,</hi> that rules us by <hi>armed Legions,</hi> as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> did the <hi>Jews,</hi> that we ſhould attempt by <hi>wars</hi> and <hi>fightings</hi> to ſhake off that Iron yoke. God himſelf hath ruled us by ſuch a <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>peaceable Princes,</hi> ever ſince the <hi>Marian</hi> days, as the whole world cannot pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel: and to raiſe <hi>tumults</hi> and <hi>wars</hi> to alter <hi>ſuch a Succeſſion,</hi> is to take the power out of Gods hands, <hi>who ruleth in the Kingdoms of the earth, and appointeth over them whomſoever he will,</hi> Dan. 5.21. And that dear experience of <hi>diſputing the Succeſſion by the Sword</hi> between the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> between whom were fought Seventeen pitcht Battles, in which periſhed Eight Kings and Princes, Forty Dukes, Marqueſſes and Earls, Two hundred thouſand of the people, beſides Barons and Gentlemen, and the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Devaſtions not to be valued, ſhould forever affright us from the like attempts, leſt we be <hi>found to fight againſt God,</hi> as well as <hi>againſt one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor is there any pretence of a <hi>Superior</hi> or <hi>co-ordinate power</hi> that may rival the Crown, the King being acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged <hi>the only Supreme Potentate, &amp;c</hi> he beareth the Sword by <hi>Gods Commiſſion,</hi> and by the <hi>Law of the Land</hi> hath the diſpoſing of the <hi>Militia:</hi> to him belongs the <hi>jus belli &amp; pacis:</hi> nor <hi>Pope</hi> nor <hi>Prelate, Presbyter</hi> or <hi>People,</hi> or their <hi>Repreſentatives,</hi> have any ſhare in the <hi>Supremacy.</hi> And yet on ſuch <hi>Paradoxes</hi> have ſome men grounded the late Wars: <hi>Prove</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>that the King was the only Supreme, and I will yield my neck to the block.</hi> I think neither the Neck nor Head of that man was far from the Block, that preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to vent ſuch a <hi>Treaſonable poſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Nor can any complaint of <hi>Tyranny</hi> or <hi>oppreſſion</hi> juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a <hi>War</hi> among us; no Nation under Heaven enjoying more <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> Temporal or Spiritual <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges</hi> than we. Although if we did ſuffer under ſome <hi>miſcarriages</hi> in Government, ſome <hi>paſſions</hi> and <hi>exceſſes</hi> in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96116:12"/>our Governours, neither <hi>Scripture</hi> nor <hi>Reaſon</hi> will warrant any <hi>reſiſtance;</hi> and <hi>experience the Miſtreſs of Fools,</hi> may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us, that <hi>the remedy would be worſe than the diſeaſe;</hi> and that they who by <hi>fears and jealouſies</hi> of <hi>Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and promiſes of <hi>liberty,</hi> and <hi>redreſs of grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſteal the hearts of the people</hi> from their Prince, as <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> did, do prove their greateſt Oppreſſors. There have been but few <hi>Tyrants</hi> under whom their peaceable Subjects have not been much happier, than under a ſtate of <hi>Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> and <hi>Confuſion.</hi> More innocent blood was ſhed, more Eſtates confiſcate, more Temples, Caſtles, and Houſes rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, more Orphans and Widows made in one year during our Civil Wars, than in all the Reigns of the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by any Tyrannical acts of theirs in 500 years. The <hi>Perſians</hi> therefore after the death of their Kings, allowed the liberty of five days, wherein every one might do as <hi>when there was no King in Iſrael,</hi> to convince them that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the worſt Governours is better than to have none.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Nor can any plea from <hi>Religion</hi> warrant <hi>wars</hi> and <hi>fightings</hi> among us: for we are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and not <hi>Jews;</hi> and we are under ſuch obligations to <hi>peace,</hi> that unleſs we can produce as clear warrant from Scripture for <hi>war</hi> and <hi>fightings</hi> among our ſelves, we act more like <hi>Pagans</hi> than <hi>Chriſtians. Peace</hi> is the <hi>laſt legacy</hi> that our Saviour left us, and by his Apoſtle he enjoyned us, <hi>if it be poſſible, and as much as in us lyeth, to live peaceably with all men:</hi> and he makes <hi>peace</hi> a condition equal with <hi>Holineſs, without which we can never ſee God.</hi> On which grounds the Primitive Chriſtians thought it unlawful to exerciſe <hi>war</hi> on any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever; they were enjoyned to take up the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and not the <hi>Sword;</hi> they were to <hi>love their enemies,</hi> and not to <hi>hate their friends:</hi> they <hi>prayed</hi> for thoſe that <hi>perſecuted them,</hi> but did not perſecute thoſe who <hi>prayed with and for them.</hi> The Apoſtles of our Lord did by preaching the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96116:13"/>Goſpel <hi>ſubdue Kingdoms,</hi> but they <hi>wrought righteouſneſs</hi> too, and did more for the <hi>ſecuring the Imperial Crowns,</hi> than all their <hi>own Laws</hi> could do. And this was one argument by which <hi>Tertullian</hi> recommended the Chriſtians to the <hi>cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency</hi> of the <hi>Roman Emperours,</hi> That none of them were <hi>Nigriani</hi> or <hi>Caſſiani,</hi> they never abetted the Rebellions of <hi>Niger</hi> or <hi>Caſſius.</hi> And this ſhould for ever endear the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that as it teacheth, <hi>That it is not lawful on any pretence whatſoever to take up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King;</hi> ſo it was the teſtimony of the <hi>Royal Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> to our <hi>preſent Soveraign,</hi> that <hi>ſcarce any one who was a beginner or active proſecutor of the late war, was a true lover, embracer, or practiſer of the Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed in</hi> England, <hi>which neither gave ſuch rules, or ſet ſuch examples.</hi> And on the contrary, ever ſince thoſe <hi>twin-Monſters</hi> of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitiſm</hi> and <hi>Fanaticiſm</hi> were born into the world together, there hath not been one conſiderable <hi>League, Covenant,</hi> or <hi>Aſſociation</hi> of people againſt their Prince, any ſingle <hi>Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> of Kings, or <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of the people, any <hi>Conſults</hi> for <hi>Diviſion, War,</hi> and <hi>Confuſion;</hi> but one or more of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave of Rome,</hi> or <hi>Conventicles of Separatiſts,</hi> and both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretence of <hi>zeal for Religion,</hi> have been the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers and executioners of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But it hath been objected, that the <hi>Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> had no <hi>Laws</hi> to confirm their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> as we have; and therefore it was not ſo lawful for them to defend their Religion by Arms as it is for us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It is ſtrange that our <hi>Laws</hi> ſhould be made a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> which declare that <hi>it is not lawful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on any pretence whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> who never bore Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>perſecuting Princes,</hi> would much more abhor to do it againſt <hi>Chriſtian Governours</hi> that favoured and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected them; they would never turn the <hi>Laws</hi> againſt the <hi>Law-makers</hi> and uſe them as <hi>Forts</hi> and <hi>Sanctuaries</hi> to ſecure and protect <hi>Rebels.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96116:13"/>
            <p n="3">3. If this plea might be admitted, the <hi>beſt Princes</hi> would be in <hi>most danger:</hi> for by this rule, if we lived under a <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>perſecuting Prince,</hi> that never favoured us with one <hi>good Law,</hi> we might not reſiſt him; but if under a Prince that made it his buſineſs to <hi>ſecure Religion</hi> by the <hi>beſt Laws,</hi> ſuch as preſume they are of a <hi>better Religion</hi> than their <hi>Prince,</hi> and can judge of the <hi>Laws</hi> better than the <hi>Law-giver,</hi> might juſtifie a <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt him; and ſo the <hi>beſt Prince</hi> would be <hi>moſt miſerable;</hi> and the ſame Laws that <hi>ſecure our Religion,</hi> would <hi>deſtroy his Crown.</hi> On ſuch a principle, when Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> came to the Crown, and found <hi>Popery</hi> eſtabliſhed by a Law, her Popiſh Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, which were then the greateſt number, might have rebelled againſt her; which yet they durſt not do on this <hi>falſe principle</hi> of ſome <hi>true Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. If Subjects may <hi>reſiſt</hi> as often as <hi>diſcontented</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning men</hi> ſhall tell them that the <hi>King</hi> doth not favour that Religion which the <hi>Laws</hi> do, and ſhall influence the people with <hi>fears and jealouſies</hi> that their <hi>Religion is in danger,</hi> and make them <hi>Judges</hi> of the <hi>Actions</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of their <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors;</hi> the <hi>beſt of Princes,</hi> who certainly ought to have ſome allowance for <hi>humane paſſions</hi> and <hi>infirmities</hi> as well as other men, would daily forfeit their <hi>Crowns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But laſtly, when the <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> which we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs is <hi>eſtabliſhed by Law,</hi> how vile and abſurd is the pretence of thoſe men for <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> who live in <hi>open defiance</hi> of thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> and in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to that <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> which is <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> by them! to which if they did with Chriſtian meekneſs conform, there would be <hi>no hurting nor deſtroying</hi> in all the Land. And if neither <hi>Religion</hi> nor <hi>Law</hi> will warrant <hi>wars</hi> and <hi>fightings</hi> among us, then the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Conſcience</hi> will vaniſh: for <hi>Conſcience</hi> is nothing elſe but a <hi>conformity</hi> of our actions to the <hi>known Laws</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and of <hi>our Superiors</hi> not contrary to the Laws of God. Now when the Law of God ſays we muſt <hi>obey our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96116:14"/>for Conſcience ſake,</hi> and our Superiors command nothing contrary to thoſe Laws, which Laws <hi>forbid us to reſiſt on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretence whatſoever,</hi> there can be neither <hi>Law</hi> nor <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to <hi>juſtifie Reſiſtance;</hi> but it proceeds from the luſts of ungodly men: whereof this is a certain proof, that when ſuch <hi>Pretenders</hi> to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> do ſucceed in their <hi>Rebellion,</hi> the <hi>Cloak</hi> is thrown off, and thoſe luſts which ſeemed <hi>dormant</hi> or <hi>couchant,</hi> appear <hi>rampant;</hi> and <hi>grievous Wolves</hi> creep out from under the <hi>Sheeps clothing,</hi> which <hi>ſpare neither Sheep nor Shepherds,</hi> nor thoſe that helped to run down the Prey with them, ſo they may <hi>kill and take poſſeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus proved our Apoſtles aſſertion in general, That <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Fightings</hi> among us can proceed from no other cauſe but <hi>our Luſts,</hi> I ſhall onely point you to a few of thoſe <hi>Luſts</hi> that are the <hi>principal Incendiaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt and chieftain of which, is that <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory</hi> which abounds in the hearts of <hi>Phariſaical men,</hi> who ſeek to have <hi>their Perſons had in admiration, becauſe of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage;</hi> and for want of <hi>ordinary qualifications,</hi> and <hi>honeſt means,</hi> pretend to <hi>extraordinary gifts</hi> and <hi>revelations of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>ſpeak great words of vanity, or by fair ſpeeches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the hearts of the ſimple; and ſpeak perverſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine received from the Apoſtles, to draw away Diſciples after them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Joſephus</hi> relates the miſerable <hi>Wars of the Jews,</hi> he gives us an account of the ſeveral <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Sects</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that acted in thoſe Wars; ſuch as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces,</hi> the <hi>Eſſenes</hi> and the <hi>Zealous,</hi> who were the chief Boutefeus. And our Saviour and his Apoſtles obſerve the like method, forewarning us of <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts</hi> or <hi>Sect-makers,</hi> as St. <hi>Jude</hi> calls them. <hi>Beware</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>of falſe prophets, which come to you in ſheeps clothing, but inwardly they are ravenous wolves,</hi> Mat. 7.15. And <hi>Acts</hi> 20.30. <hi>I know that after my departure grievous
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96116:14"/>wolves ſhall enter among you, not ſparing the flock.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo (2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.1.) ſays, <hi>There were falſe prophets among the people, as there ſhall alſo be among you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable Doctrines, denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction: and many ſhall follow their pernitious ways, by reaſon of whom the way of truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of: and through covetouſneſs ſhall they with feigned words make merchandize of you.</hi> Now that theſe men ſerved their own bellies, and not the Laws of Chriſt, St. <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17, 18. <hi>I beſeech you brethren, mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void them: for ſuch ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own bellies.</hi> And in the ſecond to <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. he tells us, that <hi>in the laſt days ſome that had a form of Godlineſs, Schemes</hi> and <hi>Syſtems, Confeſſions</hi> and <hi>Sermons</hi> of <hi>purer Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> ſhould cauſe <hi>perilous times;</hi> for they ſhould be <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, boaſters, proud, blaſphemers,—Traytors, heady, and high minded. From ſuch</hi> he adviſeth us to <hi>turn away.</hi> St. <hi>Jude</hi> alſo in his Epiſtle gives the like character of ſome that made great pretences to the Spirit, as if they did <hi>preach</hi> and <hi>pray,</hi> and do all things <hi>by the Spirit;</hi> yet they did <hi>walk af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own ungodly luſts, deſpiſed Dominions, and ſpake evil of Dignities;</hi> againſt whom St. <hi>Jude</hi> denounceth a woe: <hi>Woe unto them, for they have gone in the way of Cain,</hi> who was a Murtherer, <hi>and run greedily after the errour of Balaam for reward, and periſhed in the gainſaying of Core;</hi> who brought ſuch <hi>railing accuſations againſt Moſes and Aaron, as the Devil himſelf durſt not do. Theſe are they</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>who ſeparate themſelves; ſenſual, having not the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> v. 19.</p>
            <p>Theſe Scriptures are ſufficient to remove the prejudice which ſome people conceive againſt their Superiours for <hi>ſuppreſſing</hi> of ſuch <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> as they find ſeducing the People. The onely difficulty is, how we may <hi>diſcern falſe Prophets,</hi> ſeeing our Saviour ſays they ſhall come <hi>in Sheeps
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96116:15"/>clothing,</hi> and <hi>transform themſelves into Angels of light.</hi> Yet our Saviour's rule is infallible, <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall know them:</hi> for firſt, they ſhall come to you, come <hi>privily, creep into your houſes;</hi> come <hi>with fair words and feigned ſpeeches;</hi> come without a <hi>Call</hi> or <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Man;</hi> come againſt the <hi>eſtabliſhed Laws,</hi> and ſevereſt penalties of <hi>Fines</hi> and <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> it ſelf. Thus the <hi>Romiſh Wolves</hi> come clothed with the Name of the <hi>immaculate Lamb</hi> of God; <hi>Jeſuits</hi> they call themſelves, but <hi>grievous Wolves</hi> the Scripture terms ſuch, who <hi>aſſaſſinate</hi> the <hi>chief Shepherds</hi> in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and <hi>maſſacre whole Flocks;</hi> that with <hi>Elymas the Sorcerer</hi> ſeek to <hi>turn our Deputies from the Faith,</hi> and as the <hi>Phariſees, compaſs Sea and Land to make Proſelytes, and to make them twofold more the children of wrath</hi> and malice <hi>than themſelves.</hi> Theſe perſwade their Diſciples that they are of that <hi>holy Church in which alone Salvation is to be had;</hi> that all others out of <hi>their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> are <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> fit onely for a <hi>fiery Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory:</hi> but if they return to the <hi>Lap of their Mother,</hi> they are as <hi>ſure of Salvation</hi> as if they were in <hi>Abraham's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as our Saviour ſays, <hi>By their fruits</hi> (i. e.) their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> and their <hi>Practices, ye ſhall know them.</hi> One General Rule we have in <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1. That <hi>if a prophet ſhould ariſe that ſhould ſhew ſignes and wonders that ſhould come to paſs, yet if that prophet ſhould entice the people to idolatry</hi> (and by conſequence to any iniquity) <hi>thou ſhalt not hearken to that prophet.</hi> When therefore theſe <hi>Emiſſaries of Rome</hi> ſhall teach <hi>contrary to what we have received</hi> from Chriſt and his Apoſtles; when they perſwade us to <hi>worſhip the Creature with that Worſhip which is due onely to the Creator,</hi> be they <hi>Saints,</hi> or <hi>Angels,</hi> or the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> who all abhor to have God robbed of his Honour, of which he is <hi>a jealous God;</hi> when they adde <hi>new Articles of Faith,</hi> and <hi>Rules of Obedience,</hi> beſides and contrary to what God in his Word
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96116:15"/>hath required, and prefer their <hi>own Traditions</hi> and <hi>Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> above his <hi>expreſs Commands</hi> and <hi>Inſtitutions:</hi> when they ſow <hi>Tares in Chriſts field,</hi> and ſeek to divide his Flock; when they ſeek to advance the <hi>Intereſt of the Pope,</hi> above the <hi>Supremacy of the King,</hi> and withdraw that <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Subjection</hi> from <hi>him,</hi> which <hi>every Soul</hi> is required to yield unto him; when they teach the Doctrine of <hi>Infallibility</hi> in the <hi>Pope,</hi> though he decree things <hi>contrary to Chriſt,</hi> as in taking the <hi>Cup</hi> from the <hi>Laity,</hi> with a <hi>Non Obſtante</hi> that Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Drink ye all of this:</hi> when they decree what is contrary to <hi>Senſe,</hi> as well as the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> in the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> and other things contrary to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as in <hi>Prayers in an unknown Tongue,</hi> and <hi>denying the uſe of the Scriptures to the People,</hi> whom God commands to <hi>ſearch the Scriptures, becauſe in them we have eternal life:</hi> In a word, when they practiſe <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Cruelty,</hi> and ſtir up <hi>Strife,</hi> and foment <hi>Diviſions,</hi> and plot for <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> amongſt us; let them boaſt of <hi>Miracles</hi> and <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> of <hi>Tradition</hi> and <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> of <hi>Grandeur</hi> and <hi>Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> let them appear not onely as <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> but <hi>Angels of Light,</hi> yet if their <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> be ſuch as theſe, we muſt <hi>reſiſt them ſtedfaſt in the Faith;</hi> unleſs we will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> for a <hi>blind Obedience,</hi> our <hi>Scripture</hi> for <hi>Traditions,</hi> our <hi>Liturgie</hi> for <hi>Legends,</hi> our <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty</hi> for <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and our <hi>Peace</hi> for <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Fightings,</hi> or <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is <hi>another ſort</hi> of <hi>pernicious Creatures</hi> among our ſelves, but of a <hi>ſoreign breed;</hi> whoſe clothing is a <hi>Cloak of Zeal</hi> for <hi>Religion,</hi> with <hi>broad Phylacteries,</hi> and <hi>ſentences of Scripture;</hi> their diſcourſe is of <hi>ſoft Murmurings</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints</hi> againſt the <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>loud Outcries</hi> againſt the <hi>Romiſh Wolves,</hi> that we may not <hi>ſuſpect danger</hi> from any <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quarter.</hi> And the better to <hi>draw away Diſciples after them,</hi> they come with <hi>demure looks,</hi> and <hi>dejected Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> and, as the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> pretend to great <hi>Myſteries</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96116:16"/>
               <hi>Revelations, extraordinary and immediate aſſiſtances of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>purer Ordinances;</hi> that with them is the <hi>Scepter of Chriſts holy Diſcipline,</hi> to which all <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>People</hi> muſt bow, or ſhall be <hi>broken in pieces;</hi> for God will <hi>reprove even Kings for their ſakes, ſaying, Touch not mine Anointed, and do my Prophets no harm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>by their fruits</hi> we ſhall know <hi>theſe men</hi> alſo: for how oppoſite ſoever they ſeem to be to the <hi>Romiſh Wolves</hi> in their Profeſſions, they are coupled as <hi>Sampſon's foxes with fire-brands in their tails,</hi> by deſtructive Principles and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices againſt the <hi>eſtabliſhed Church and Government.</hi> As <hi>Herod</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> the <hi>Roman,</hi> were againſt Chriſt. It would fill a Volume to diſcover the <hi>Intrigues</hi> of <hi>theſe two Factions;</hi> how mutually they aſſiſt each other with <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Arguments</hi> againſt <hi>their common Enemy.</hi> They are conſcious that they are <hi>too weak ſingly</hi> to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>eſtabliſhed Government;</hi> and therefore will not ſuffer either to be utterly <hi>ſuppreſſed;</hi> nor will the <hi>Jealouſie</hi> of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Party ſuffer the other to be <hi>uppermoſt,</hi> leſt they ſhould carry away the whole Prey. So that we are kept as <hi>good Grain</hi> between <hi>two Mill-ſtones of an equal ſize,</hi> till we are <hi>ground to duſt;</hi> and then they will <hi>grinde the faces of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I take thoſe, and onely thoſe, who do agree with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in preaching and propagating ſeditious and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Principles and Practices, ſuch as <hi>The lawfulneſs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance,</hi> and <hi>taking up Arms in defence of Religion</hi> againſt the Supreme Magiſtrate; <hi>That the Original of the Magiſtrates power is in the people, who may call them to an account, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or murther them as they ſee cauſe;</hi> That would erect <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Supremacy</hi> in the <hi>Pope, Parliament,</hi> or <hi>Presbytery;</hi> that ſecretly <hi>conſpire the death of their Prince,</hi> or <hi>raiſe Open Wars</hi> to effect the ſame; thoſe who have murthered <hi>one King</hi> already, and uſe the ſame methods to <hi>deſtroy another;</hi> that oppoſe, defame, and condemn men of Peaceable, Loyal,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96116:16"/>and Chriſtian Principles, and <hi>Canonize Traytors</hi> and <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides</hi> as <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs;</hi> and in a word, all ſuch as <hi>will not declare that it is unlawful to take up Arms againſt the King on any pretence whatſoever,</hi> or <hi>that they will not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour any alteration of the eſtabliſhed Government;</hi> they whoſe <hi>Sermons</hi> are <hi>Satyrs</hi> againſt their <hi>Governours;</hi> whoſe <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is of <hi>Curſing</hi> and <hi>Lies,</hi> and their <hi>Practice</hi> to raiſe <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Fightings</hi> among us, for ſuch <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our bids us to <hi>beware of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe men do indeed abhor the <hi>name</hi> and <hi>doom</hi> of <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> let them do what they can and ought to do to clear themſelves: let them <hi>expunge</hi> out of their <hi>Books</hi> ſuch <hi>traiterous Principles,</hi> and <hi>anathematize</hi> them in their <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles;</hi> let them follow that worthy Example of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and that of the Converts, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.19. bring thoſe <hi>conjuring Books together,</hi> that can raiſe up <hi>Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Evil Spirits,</hi> and without counting the <hi>value</hi> of them, though it be 50000 pieces of ſilver, <hi>publickly burn them:</hi> And they will make as <hi>comfortable a Bonfire</hi> as ever the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſaw, except that of <hi>New-Market.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if they will ſtill go on as thoſe falſe Prophets, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.14. <hi>to ſtrengthen the hands of evil doers, that none doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from their wickedneſs:</hi> if they will publickly <hi>deſpiſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and ſpeak evil of Dignities;</hi> and <hi>one Party</hi> condemn <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People</hi> as <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> fit to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the Sword, or to paſs through a <hi>Fiery Purgatory;</hi> and the other accuſe us as <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> though they know not whether <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Magog,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtianiſſimus</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtianiſſimus</hi> be the <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> but whoever he be, they are more ready to be reconciled to him, than to the <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Government eſtabliſhed;</hi> they ſhall never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to wipe off the guilt, or eſcape the doom of <hi>falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> as long as they teach ſuch <hi>Damnable Doctrines:</hi> for ſo the Scripture hath determined it, <hi>They that reſiſt, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to themſelves damnation,</hi> Rom. 13.2.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:96116:17"/>
            <p>And yet, as if the <hi>Genius of the Nation</hi> inclined them to <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Fightings,</hi> how do we (like children) in every City and Market-town flock after theſe <hi>Drums</hi> and <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets</hi> that ſound an <hi>Alarm</hi> to <hi>Wars,</hi> and inſtead of <hi>the Goſpel of peace,</hi> propagate an <hi>Evangelium Armatum,</hi> the Law of the Sword; that maintain <hi>unlawful meetings</hi> for the <hi>muſtering of their Forces,</hi> and make their <hi>Exerciſes</hi> like thoſe of the <hi>Artilleries,</hi> to diſcipline the People for <hi>War;</hi> and can, as by a <hi>word of command,</hi> lead them from their <hi>Folds</hi> into the <hi>Field,</hi> and arm them with <hi>Zeal</hi> enough to <hi>murther</hi> their Brethren, their <hi>Biſhop,</hi> their <hi>Prince,</hi> and in a little time <hi>one another!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not, certainly, the <hi>Goſpel of peace</hi> which theſe men <hi>preach;</hi> that would transform <hi>Lions into Lambs,</hi> but their <hi>Harangues</hi> transform <hi>Lambs</hi> into <hi>Lions</hi> and <hi>Tygers:</hi> that would teach men to <hi>beat their Swords into Plowſhares,</hi> this teacheth them to <hi>beat up their Plowſhares</hi> and ſilver <hi>Bodkins</hi> and <hi>Thimbles</hi> into <hi>Swords</hi> and <hi>Piſtols.</hi> And between the <hi>Faux</hi>'s of this Age, who with their <hi>dark Lanthorns</hi> and <hi>lighted Fire-brands,</hi> are ready to <hi>give fire</hi> to their <hi>ſubterranean Mines,</hi> and are ſorry for nothing but their diſappointment; and thoſe <hi>Blunderbuſſes,</hi> who being <hi>full charged</hi> to the very mouths with <hi>Powder</hi> and <hi>Bullet,</hi> and have <hi>Zeal</hi> enough, though their <hi>hearts</hi> be <hi>as hard as Flint or Steel,</hi> to give fire in the face of <hi>Majeſty</hi> it ſelf; we are ſtill between the Jaws of thoſe <hi>roaring Lions,</hi> that <hi>go about ſeeking how they may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour us.</hi> And had not the Almighty hand of God reſtrained theſe <hi>Sons of Violence,</hi> and kept them back with more than <hi>Bit and Bridle,</hi> they would have long ſince fallen on us, and rent us in pieces.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, even the God of our Salvation, our Deliverer and Defender, who hath hewn the <hi>Snares</hi> of <hi>thoſe ungodly men</hi> in pieces; and though they have <hi>often aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted us from our youth up,</hi> ye he hath not <hi>delivered us o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as a prey unto their teeth.</hi> And may we never provoke
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96116:17"/>him by our <hi>murmurings</hi> and <hi>diſcontent,</hi> our <hi>hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>profaneneſs,</hi> our <hi>diviſions</hi> and <hi>luſting after evil things,</hi> to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent him</hi> of all the loving kindneſs and wonders of mercy which he hath wrought for us; which if they lead us not to <hi>repentance</hi> and <hi>amendment of life,</hi> will render us more fit for deſtruction; and then in vain may we hope for <hi>another miracle,</hi> to deliver us from thoſe <hi>fiery furnaces</hi> which theſe <hi>lurking firebrands</hi> have prepared for us; and by their <hi>indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> ſince our <hi>miraculous deliverance</hi> from the <hi>Lions den,</hi> and their <hi>as wonderful diſappointments,</hi> are <hi>heated ſeven times hotter</hi> than ever: for their wickedneſs ſtill <hi>burneth like fire,</hi> and is like that <hi>worſt ſort</hi> of fire, which <hi>goeth not out,</hi> though never ſo many waters of <hi>clemency</hi> and <hi>favours</hi> be poured on it: they have the effect of Oyl and Fuel, to <hi>increaſe,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to <hi>extinguiſh</hi> the flame. For they have provided that their <hi>malice</hi> may <hi>ſurvive themſelves,</hi> and be <hi>immortal;</hi> they have incloſed their <hi>Seminaries</hi> for <hi>Briers,</hi> and <hi>Thorns,</hi> and <hi>Brambles,</hi> out of which a <hi>fire</hi> may come in time, to <hi>burn up all the Cedars in Lebanon;</hi> and they have fitted their <hi>Nurſeries</hi> for <hi>another generation</hi> of <hi>Vipers,</hi> who ſuck in their <hi>poyſonous principles,</hi> and are armed with <hi>invincible prejudices</hi> againſt that <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> which is eſtabliſhed among us: like ſome <hi>plodding Spaniards</hi> at their <hi>game at Cheſs,</hi> who having not time or ſucceſs ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to blow off their <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and give check to their <hi>Kings,</hi> leave the game to be played out by their Succeſſors. For from the <hi>poiſonous principles</hi> that fall from their <hi>lips,</hi> as from the <hi>Serpents teeth</hi> in the <hi>Poet,</hi> there ſpring up a <hi>numerous brood</hi> of <hi>armed men,</hi> who are as deaf to <hi>ſober counſels</hi> and <hi>arguments for peace</hi> and <hi>unity,</hi> as the very <hi>Adders,</hi> and as ready as ſo many <hi>Swine</hi> to <hi>turn on them and rent them</hi> who <hi>caſt thoſe Pearls before them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid, <hi>that few men dye without a Feaver;</hi> and as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that there was <hi>not one</hi> of thoſe who were <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> for the late <hi>horrid Conſpiracy,</hi> whom the <hi>prejudices</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:96116:18"/>which <hi>fermented their ſpirits</hi> from their <hi>Childhood,</hi> did not <hi>ſwell</hi> and make <hi>ſower,</hi> and <hi>animate them</hi> to thoſe <hi>deſperate deſigns</hi> which brought them to thoſe untimely ends. Thus that degenerate Gentleman Mr. SIDNEY, had no other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology for himſelf, than <hi>that he had been managed from his youth in that</hi> OLD CAUSE, which was begun in <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and carryed on with <hi>confuſed noiſe, and garments rolled in blood.</hi> And <hi>another</hi> as unfortunate as himſelf, had thoſe principles of the <hi>lawfulneſs of Reſiſtance</hi> in caſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> infuſed to him by <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> from his youth, which were the <hi>venemous ingredients</hi> to his death. The Author of the <hi>Life of Julian</hi> had (it ſeems) confirmed him in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of what Dr <hi>Manton</hi> had long before inſtructed him in; who on this very Text raiſeth the Queſtion, <hi>Whether Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion may be defended by Arms?</hi> to which, among other things, he anſwereth, <hi>That ſometime the outward exerciſe of Religion and Worſhip may be eſtabliſhed and ſecured by Laws; and among other priviledges and rights, the liberty of pure worſhip may be one; which being invaded by violence, may be defended by Arms —The Eſtates of a Kingdom may main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Religion againſt the tyranny and malice of the Prince.</hi> And on <hi>theſe prejudices</hi> dyed the <hi>whole Colledge</hi> of the late <hi>Conſpirators;</hi> whoſe blood may be <hi>required</hi> at their <hi>hands</hi> that corrupted their <hi>hearts</hi> with ſuch <hi>blood-guilty prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi> For <hi>from hence come wars and fightings among us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Next to the luſts of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>vain-glory,</hi> St. <hi>James</hi> doth arraign thoſe of <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>malice,</hi> as the <hi>cauſe of wars:</hi> for he tells us, That <hi>the ſpirit that dwelleth in us luſteth to envy,</hi> v. 5. and <hi>where envying and ſtrife is, there is confuſion, and every evil thing,</hi> Jam. 3.16. And if there be <hi>bitter zeal</hi> or <hi>envyings</hi> and <hi>ſtrife</hi> among us, that <hi>it proceeds from the devil, who was a murtherer from the beginning,</hi> and is <hi>reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> till he draw others under the ſame condemnation with himſelf: for the <hi>envious man</hi> is <hi>felo de ſe;</hi> he <hi>ſeeds</hi> on his own <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>bowels,</hi> and leaves no <hi>bowels of pity</hi> for any
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96116:18"/>that he thinks in a <hi>better condition than himſelf:</hi> 'tis this that is <hi>the rottenneſs of the bones,</hi> Prov. 14.30. This <hi>ſlayeth thoſe ſilly ones</hi> that entertain it, <hi>Job</hi> 5.2. and <hi>none is able to ſtand before it, Prov.</hi> 27.4. And next to <hi>Envy followeth Murder,</hi> Rom. 1.29. Gal. 5.21. The <hi>firſt Murder</hi> in the world was committed <hi>through Envy</hi> againſt a Brother. <hi>Wherefore did Cain ſlay Abel, but through envy, his own works being evil, and his Brothers righteous?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Acts 7.9. <hi>the Patriarchs moved with envy ſold Joſeph to Egypt.</hi> As ſoon as they underſtood he was to be preferred <hi>above them,</hi> they <hi>could not ſpeak peaceably to him, Gen.</hi> 37.4. becauſe his Father loved him more than them: and <hi>v.</hi> 20. they <hi>conſpire</hi> againſt him: <hi>Come, let us ſlay him, and caſt him into a pit.</hi> It was for <hi>Envy</hi> that the <hi>chief Prieſts</hi> and <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Jews</hi> delivered our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.18. and purſued him with outcries, <hi>Crucifie him, Crucifie him;</hi> and, <hi>let his blood be upon us and our Children:</hi> by which <hi>impiety</hi> they ſhewed themſelves to be <hi>the children of them that had ſlain the Prophets, and filled up the meaſure of their iniquities;</hi> and drew down on <hi>themſelves</hi> and the <hi>whole Nation</hi> all thoſe <hi>Judgments</hi> of which I have told you, when God <hi>viſited on them all the righteous blood that had been ſhed from the blood of</hi> Abel <hi>to the blood of Chriſt himſelf;</hi> which brought them to a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>utter deſolation;</hi> which <hi>Joſephus</hi> their Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Judgment worthy of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſhedding of blood,</hi> though of his own and Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſo diſpleaſed the Lord, that he would not permit <hi>David</hi> to build him a Temple; that work was reſerved for a <hi>peaceable Solomon:</hi> and if any mans hands be <hi>defiled with blood, though he make never ſo many prayers he will not hear,</hi> till he have <hi>cleanſed his heart, and waſhed his hands in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency;</hi> and not till then, may he <hi>have acceſs to Gods Altar.</hi> The <hi>blood-guiltineſs</hi> of a <hi>few,</hi> draweth down the wrath of God on a <hi>whole Nation.</hi> There was a <hi>Famine</hi> on <hi>Iſrael three years together</hi> in the time of <hi>David;</hi> and when he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96116:19"/>inquired the cauſe of it, it was revealed to be <hi>for Saul and for his bloudy houſe,</hi> that ſlew the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> 2 Sam. 21.1. And if the bloud of the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> was avenged not onely <hi>ſevenfold</hi> on the houſe of <hi>Saul;</hi> by <hi>hanging up ſeven of his Sons,</hi> but upon <hi>all Iſrael</hi> by <hi>three years famine;</hi> we may juſtly impute the <hi>conſuming Peſtilence</hi> and <hi>Fires</hi> that have been among us, to the ſhedding of <hi>much more innocent bloud.</hi> And we may juſtly fear, that the <hi>inquiſition</hi> for <hi>that bloud</hi> is not yet ended: for <hi>bloud defileth the land;</hi> and it <hi>cannot be cleanſed</hi> but by the <hi>bloud of them that ſhed it,</hi> unleſs it be prevented by a <hi>deep</hi> and <hi>timely repentance,</hi> and the <hi>avenging</hi> it on <hi>our ſelves,</hi> by a <hi>hearty ſorrow,</hi> by a <hi>ſerious mortification</hi> of <hi>thoſe luſts</hi> that provoked us thereunto, and a <hi>thorow refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> and <hi>amendment</hi> of our ſinful ways and doings; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we <hi>cry mightily</hi> to God for pardon, and the <hi>bloud of Chriſt, which ſpeaketh better things than that of Abel,</hi> be joyned with our <hi>Cries</hi> and <hi>Tears.</hi> Without ſhedding of <hi>more bloud,</hi> there will be <hi>no remiſſion:</hi> for the cry of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud is not to be ſilenced by any earthly thing, but will enter <hi>into the ears of the Lord of Sabboth</hi> with an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque quo Domine? How long, O Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not judge and avenge our bloud on them that dwell on the earth?</hi> Revel. 6.10.</p>
            <p>And when we ſee <hi>Rebellion</hi> to be <hi>like the ſin of witchcraft,</hi> which ſeldom or never admits repentance: when <hi>not one</hi> of the <hi>old Regicides</hi> or <hi>new Conſpirators,</hi> though they confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the fact for which they died, profeſſed any <hi>Regret</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> for it (which yet in the Caſe of Chriſt <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> did, and every <hi>common Murtherer</hi> is wont to do:) when there are ſtill ſo many among us that <hi>approve</hi> of thoſe <hi>horrid Impieties</hi> of their <hi>Forefathers,</hi> and onely <hi>want Opportunities</hi> to act over the ſame <hi>Tragedies</hi> again: when men are ready to caſt <hi>Fire-brands, Arrows,</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> and think it a <hi>Sport:</hi> when God <hi>infatuates</hi> a People, and <hi>delivers them up to ſuch ſtrong deluſions,</hi> and <hi>faſcinations,</hi> that not all
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96116:19"/>the <hi>Oracles of God,</hi> nor all the <hi>Examples</hi> of <hi>Divine Vengeance</hi> and <hi>Humane Juſtice</hi> can <hi>awaken them,</hi> and reduce them to a <hi>ſounder mind; neither if one ſhould ariſe from the dead, will they repent.</hi> And whether it be that God hath given up ſuch Offenders to a <hi>reprobate mind,</hi> or with <hi>Cain</hi> they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend <hi>their ſins greater than can be forgiven, or that God</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered them up to the <hi>furies</hi> of their <hi>guilty Conſciences,</hi> and hath ſentenced them to thoſe <hi>Chains of impenitence and darkneſs to the judgment of the laſt day;</hi> it is to me the moſt <hi>certain</hi> and <hi>ſad Omen,</hi> that God hath yet <hi>fuller vials of wrath</hi> to be poured out on ſuch men, at leaſt, if not on the <hi>whole Nation,</hi> againſt whom his <hi>hand</hi> is not yet withdrawn, but <hi>his arm is ſtretched out ſtill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have a <hi>day of Humiliation</hi> appointed for the barbarous <hi>Parricide</hi> of our <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> and we have had a <hi>day of Thankſgiving</hi> for the miraculous <hi>Deliverance</hi> of our <hi>preſent Soveraign,</hi> which you have this day religiouſly commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated. But while ſome <hi>mourn,</hi> and make the <hi>firſt</hi> a day of <hi>Lamentation</hi> for <hi>the Anointed of the Lord; who was taken in the pits of deceitful and bloud-thirſty men;</hi> others <hi>applaud</hi> that <hi>execrable Fact,</hi> and <hi>nouriſh their hearts as in a day of ſlaughter,</hi> or <hi>ſuch a Sacrifice wherewith God was well pleaſed:</hi> And when the <hi>ſecond</hi> is a day of <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Gladneſs</hi> to ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Proſperity,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Crown</hi> flouriſh; others <hi>mourn</hi> that their <hi>Babel is fallen:</hi> if while ſome <hi>bleſs God</hi> that hath <hi>preſerved the King</hi> and his <hi>People,</hi> others <hi>curſe the King</hi> and <hi>People</hi> whom God hath preſerved; and while theſe are <hi>perſwading to peace,</hi> they <hi>make them ready for War:</hi> what can a People <hi>ſo divided</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, but to be <hi>deſtroyed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another <hi>cauſe of War</hi> is the <hi>Amor habendi,</hi> the immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate deſire of having things that are <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> and <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> whether <hi>power, pleaſures,</hi> or <hi>poſſeſſions.</hi> For when men can ſet <hi>no bounds</hi> to their <hi>Luſts,</hi> they conſider not whether the <hi>end</hi> be neceſſary, or the <hi>means</hi> lawful, but they muſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96116:20"/>have the <hi>Rem quocunque modo rem.</hi> And ſo S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.9. <hi>They that will be rich, fall into a ſnare and temptations, and many fooliſh and hurtful luſts, that drown men in perdition;</hi> and they that are greedy of <hi>gain,</hi> will not ſtick to <hi>take away the life of the owners thereof.</hi> This our Apoſtle obſerves, when he joyns <hi>the deſire of having</hi> with <hi>killing.</hi> And our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our makes this the reaſon of the <hi>Jews killing the heir, that the inheritance might be theirs.</hi> Thus <hi>Solomon</hi> brings in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men conſpiring together, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.13. <hi>We ſhall find all precious ſubſtance, we ſhall fill our houſes with ſpoil:</hi> and then, <hi>Come, let us lay wait for bloud, let us lurk privily for the innocent without cauſe.</hi> This Luſt warreth firſt <hi>in our own members.</hi> Prov. 15.27. <hi>He that is greedy of gain, troubleth his own houſe,</hi> diſquieteth himſelf; and his deſire of having is not quenched, but with the bloud of thoſe from whom he takes. Thus <hi>Ahab</hi> was <hi>ſick at the heart</hi> for <hi>Naboth's Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,</hi> and nothing could cure him but <hi>Jezabel's Receipt</hi> of <hi>killing and taking poſſeſſion.</hi> Yet this was to be gilded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with a <hi>ſhew</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi> a <hi>ſolemn Fast muſt be proclaimed,</hi> and <hi>Naboth accuſed of blaſpheming God and the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That our <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Fightings</hi> were begun for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch <hi>covetous Luſts,</hi> the ſame method of <hi>killing and taking poſſeſſion</hi> plainly demonſtrate. The <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> ſhortly after his <hi>Coronation</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> makes a <hi>Revocation</hi> of ſuch Lands as were taken from the <hi>Crown</hi> in his Fathers Minority. Alſo ſome <hi>Noblemen</hi> and <hi>others</hi> called <hi>Lords of the Erection,</hi> or <hi>Impropriators,</hi> who had <hi>ingroſſed</hi> almoſt all the <hi>Tythes</hi> of the Nation, allowing the <hi>Miniſters</hi> an <hi>inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Pittance</hi> or <hi>Stipend,</hi> and theſe <hi>Lay-patrons,</hi> ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the <hi>Country,</hi> that no man durſt to take home his <hi>nine parts,</hi> until the <hi>Impropriators</hi> had ſet out their <hi>tenth;</hi> by means whereof, the <hi>generality</hi> had their <hi>dependance</hi> on theſe Lords, againſt whom the King received frequent <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions</hi> from the <hi>Gentry</hi> and their <hi>Farmers,</hi> as alſo the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, complaining of this Oppreſſion. Whereupon his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96116:20"/>Majeſty grants a <hi>Commiſſion of Surrendry</hi> of <hi>Superiority</hi> and <hi>Tythes,</hi> in which ſome of the <hi>intereſſed Lords</hi> were made <hi>Commiſſioners;</hi> and ſo fairly and equally was it executed, that the Lords received a <hi>competent ſatisfaction,</hi> and the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, Gentry,</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> being freed from that <hi>Vaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage,</hi> thankfully acknowledged the benefit. But the <hi>Lords</hi> perceiving they ſhould loſe the <hi>dependance</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> ſuggeſted that this was done in <hi>favour</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and to the <hi>prejudice</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi> and taking advantage of ſome other <hi>Accidents,</hi> they begin to <hi>aſſociate,</hi> and enter into a <hi>Covenant</hi> for defence of their <hi>Religion:</hi> and hence came <hi>thoſe Wars</hi> and <hi>Fightings.</hi> For the <hi>ſucceſs</hi> of the <hi>Scots</hi> againſt their <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſtirred up the <hi>like luſts</hi> in ſome <hi>Members</hi> of our <hi>Nation,</hi> who under the like pretence of <hi>Religion,</hi> and clamours of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> armed themſelves to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> and (as ſoon as they had power) to <hi>kill and take poſſeſſion:</hi> and with ſuch <hi>ample Dividends</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Crown-lands</hi> did thoſe <hi>Reformers</hi> gratifie the <hi>luſts that warred in their ſeveral members,</hi> that they proved a <hi>Snare</hi> not to <hi>themſelves</hi> onely, but to <hi>their Poſterity,</hi> who <hi>applaud their Fathers doings;</hi> and though they proved <hi>ſowre Grapes</hi> unto them, yet <hi>their childrens teeth and appetites are ſet on edge to devour things that are holy.</hi> And <hi>ſo juſt</hi> do they ſtill think their <hi>Title</hi> to <hi>thoſe Lands,</hi> that they think it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to vindicate it by a <hi>ſecond Rebellion.</hi> And <hi>hence come wars and fightings,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The laſt <hi>cauſe of War</hi> which I ſhall mention, is the <hi>want</hi> of a <hi>due conſideration</hi> of the <hi>Miſchief</hi> and <hi>evil Conſequences</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> that <hi>Pandora</hi>'s Box, whence <hi>all manner of Plagues</hi> do iſſue; peſtilential Fevers, bloudy Fluxes, Famines, Confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grations of Towns and Cities, demoliſhing of Caſtles and Temples, devaſtation of whole Countries, and introducing of Atheiſm and Barbarity: of all which this Nation hath had ſad experience: which made the Orator to ſay, <hi>Quem diſcordiae, quem Caedes Civium, quem bellum civile delectat,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96116:21"/>eum ex finibus humanae naturae exterminandum puto,</hi> Phil. 13. They who delight to live in a <hi>ſtate of War,</hi> are <hi>not fit</hi> to live <hi>in any ſtate</hi> of Mankind.</p>
            <p>Some among us have heard to what <hi>great honour</hi> the <hi>Dregs of the Nation</hi> have been advanced; how <hi>Coblers</hi> have been <hi>tranſlated</hi> to <hi>Colonels,</hi> and <hi>Clowns</hi> to <hi>Counſellors of State;</hi> how <hi>Bankrupts</hi> have become <hi>Bankers,</hi> and <hi>Apprentices Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers;</hi> and the <hi>Saint-like Souldiers</hi> have had the <hi>honour to bind Kings in Chains, and Nobles in Fetters of iron:</hi> and hence it is, that ſuch as are <hi>in debt and diſtreſs,</hi> ſuch as <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> from the <hi>eſtabliſhed Worſhip,</hi> and like <hi>Corah</hi> and his Confederates think themſelves <hi>more fit than Moſes and Aaron,</hi> aſpire to the <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry</hi> by <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</hi> But theſe <hi>ſilly men</hi> conſider not <hi>who it is</hi> that by the <hi>Chains of theſe Luſts</hi> is leading them Captive to <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Damnation:</hi> they think not what <hi>Dogs-heads</hi> they may prove, as <hi>Hazael</hi> did (who had as good a conceit of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as they) to <hi>ſlay their brethren with the ſword, and ſet on fire the ſtrong holds of Iſrael, to daſh their children, and rip up the women with child,</hi> 2 Kings 8.13. Nor do they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how <hi>ſhort</hi> and <hi>troubleſome</hi> their reign may be, and how <hi>for three tranſgreſſions and for four</hi> (i. e.) the <hi>manifold iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> whereby they <hi>threſhed their Country with inſtruments of iron,</hi> what <hi>a fire God ſent into the houſe of Hazael,</hi> Amos 1.4.</p>
            <p>I therefore beſeech thoſe that <hi>delight in making Diviſions</hi> and <hi>War</hi> among <hi>our ſelves,</hi> to conſider, firſt, how many things are <hi>neceſſarily required</hi> to make a <hi>War lawful.</hi> It is not every <hi>Offence</hi> or <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> of our <hi>Governours</hi> can warrant it; but there muſt be a <hi>ſufficient Authority;</hi> and after <hi>all poſſible endeavours, overtures,</hi> and <hi>condeſcentions for Peace,</hi> none but <hi>lawful means</hi> muſt be uſed, and thoſe proſecuted with <hi>Equity</hi> and <hi>Moderation,</hi> and all intended to a <hi>good end:</hi> which <hi>circumſtances</hi> cannot meet to juſtifie ſuch as endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Fightings</hi> among us: and therefore as <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> doth determine it, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. de Jure belli, <hi>All the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96116:21"/>Plunder and Rapine, all the Cries and Tears of Widows and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans, and the louder Cries of Innocent Bloud, will God require at their hands who have been the Contrivers and Actors in unlawful Wars.</hi> So that whether they are <hi>Conquerors</hi> or <hi>conquered,</hi> whether they <hi>ſurvive</hi> the <hi>Rebellion,</hi> or <hi>die</hi> in it, they are like to be utterly <hi>undone,</hi> if they <hi>live</hi> and <hi>proſper</hi> in their <hi>Rebellion:</hi> they live in <hi>impenitence,</hi> and never think of making that <hi>reſtitution</hi> and <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> for all the <hi>Plunder</hi> and <hi>Rapine</hi> committed by them; without which there is no remiſſion: and if they die, they die in thoſe ſins to which the Scriptures have <hi>threatned Damnation.</hi> From which, and all the <hi>cauſes</hi> thereof, eſpecially <hi>From all Sedition, privy Conſpiracy, and Rebellion; from all falſe Doctrine, Hereſie, and Schiſm; from hardneſs of heart, and contempt of Gods Word and Commandments,</hi> let us joyntly and heartily pray, <hi>The Lord to deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I ſhall not adde any thing to your own <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>Loyal Reſolutions</hi> for the preſervation of <hi>your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> from <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Confuſions.</hi> Onely give me leave to mind you of a Saying of the Lord <hi>Verulam: We have many good Laws, but there wants one great one more, to enforce the execution of all the rest.</hi> And it is certain, that many go to Hell with <hi>good intentions,</hi> for want of <hi>executing them</hi> in due ſeaſon. Let us therefore beware, leſt while we are <hi>folding our hands</hi> in ſecurity, or are but <hi>putting on our Harneſs,</hi> our <hi>Confuſions</hi> come upon us <hi>as an armed man.</hi> And though we have a <hi>proſpect</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Settlement,</hi> let us alſo look back on the <hi>Cauſes of War;</hi> and while others are <hi>united</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious</hi> to <hi>deſtroy</hi> us, let us unanimouſly and vigorouſly purſue <hi>the things that belong to our peace.</hi> And firſt let us ſuppreſs <hi>thoſe luſts that war in our own members,</hi> againſt <hi>God</hi> and our <hi>own Souls:</hi> All <hi>Intemperance</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſie, Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Ambition;</hi> all <hi>Envy, Pride,</hi> and <hi>Malice,</hi> and whatever <hi>Luſts</hi> may <hi>ſeparate between God and us,</hi> or <hi>divide us from one another;</hi> and readily <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:96116:22"/>all our <hi>private Animoſities</hi> and <hi>Intereſts</hi> to the <hi>publick Religion, Peace, and Proſperity</hi> of the Nation.</p>
            <p>It after all that hath been ſaid, there be any that ſtill <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in War,</hi> let them war that <hi>good warfare</hi> in which they have been engaged from their <hi>Baptiſm, Tanquam Sacramento Militari,</hi> to fight under their Saviours Banner <hi>against ſin, the world, and the devil.</hi> Here we want not <hi>Enemies</hi> that are conſtantly <hi>aſſaulting us;</hi> nor, if we behave our ſelves <hi>manfully,</hi> can we want a <hi>compleat Victory</hi> over them: 'tis but to <hi>deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts;</hi> and though the <hi>Devil himſelf</hi> lead them on, we may by a <hi>ſtout reſiſtance</hi> put them to flight, and ſhall be <hi>more than Conquerors.</hi> In theſe <hi>Conflicts</hi> we may outdo <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf, who having <hi>ſubdued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Kingdoms,</hi> was <hi>overcome by his own luſts;</hi> Fortior eſt qui ſe. Every one that <hi>fights the good fight of faith, overcometh the world,</hi> and ſhall receive <hi>a kingdom that cannot be moved,</hi> as the Kingdoms of this World may; and <hi>a crown that fadeth not away, reſerved for us in heaven, and ready to be revealed:</hi> for, <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>I come quickly, and my reward is with me.</hi> Even ſo come, Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96116:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
